Richard Anderson Harvill papers, 1951-1952
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Richard Anderson Harvill inauguration records, 1951-1952
AZ 314
University of Arizona
The collection contains materials relating to the inauguration of Richard Anderson Harvill, as the fourteenth president of The University of Arizona. Included are materials relating to the planning of the event including, correspondence, invitations, guest lists, and financial statements; materials from the event, including programs, photographs, and recorded addresses; and other miscellaneous materials including clippings, greetings, and lists of invitations which received no reply.
2.1 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Historical Note
The inauguration of Richard Anderson Harvill consisted of a series of major campus wide events which took place over homecoming weekend, November fifteenth through the seventeenth, 1951.
The festivities began with an informal, private dinner hosted by Dr. Harvill, at the Arizona Inn, on Thursday November fifteenth. Immediately following the dinner, was an Open House at the Arizona State Museum, presenting the new Gila Pueblo Archeological Collection donated to The University of Arizona by Mr. and Mrs. Harold S. Gladwin.
Friday, November sixteenth began with a Symposium entitled, "Arizona, Land of Promise and Fulfillment." The event was chaired by Thomas G. Chapman, Dean of the College of Mines and Metallurgy at The University of Arizona. The speakers included four past University presidents: Homer L. Shantz, Rufus B. von KleinSmid, James Byron McCormick, and Alfred Atkinson. The Symposium was followed by a luncheon at the Student Union, with Howard Pyle, Governor of Arizona, as the principal speaker.
Following the luncheon, was the formal inauguration program, presided by Robert L. Nugent, vice-president of The University of Arizona. The event featured addresses by Melvin T. Solve, Chairman of the faculty; Douglas Ward, President of the University student body; Fred Stofft, President of the University Alumni Assocation; Howard Pyle, Governor of Arizona; and Dr. J. Roscoe Miller, President of Northwestern University. Dr. Harvill's induction was presided over by Cleon T. Knapp, President of the Board of Regents of the University and State Colleges of Arizona.
Immediately following the inauguration ceremony, was a reception and the formal opening of the new Kress Collection of European Masterpieces at the University of Arizona Art Gallery. This collection consisted of 25 pieces placed on indefinite loan to The University of Arizona by the Samuel K. Kress Foundation.
Following the opening was a private performance of the musical "Brigadoon," presented by the University of Arizona College of Fine Arts for Dr. Harvill, his personal guests, and invited delegates.
Homecoming day, Saturday November seventeenth, was the formal dedication ceremony for the new Student Union Memorial Building. President Harvill was the Chairman for the event which featured addresses by former University of Arizona Presidents, James Byron McCormick, and Alfred Atkinson, and an address by Arizona Governor Howard Pyle. The dedication address was delivered by Cleon T. Knapp.
Following the dedication, was the Homecoming football game, Arizona vs. Idaho, with a special half-time presentation to the Football team of 1901, and the Silver Jubilee Celebration by the Class of 1926.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains materials relating to the inauguration of Richard Anderson Harvill, as the fourteenth president of The University of Arizona. Included are materials relating to the planning of the event including, correspondence, invitations, guest lists, and financial statements; materials from the event, including programs, photographs, and recorded addresses; and other miscellaneous materials including clippings, greetings, and lists of invitations which received no reply.
Access Terms
Harvill, Richard Anderson, 1905- -- Inauguration
Nugent, Robert Logan -- Oratory
Roscoe, J. E. (James Ernest), b. 1880 -- Oratory
Knapp, Cleon T. -- Oratory
University of Arizona -- Presidents
University of Arizona -- History
University of Arizona -- Faculty
University of Arizona -- Congresses
Correspondence
Container List
- Correspondence: Inauguration Committee, Robert L. Nugent, Chair. No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence: Governor Howard Pyle; Arizona Board of Regents; and Arizona State Officials. No Date (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Suggested list of guests; lists of delegates. No Date (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Invitations, programs, tickets, form cards, and official publications. No Date (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Publicity notices. No Date (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Financial statement for inauguration expenses. No Date (Box 1, Folder 6)
- President Harvill's personal dinner. November 15, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Symposium: "Arizona, Land of Promise and Fulfillment". Includes correspondence with speakers: Alfred Atkinson, J. Byron McCormick, Homer LeRoy Shantz, and Rufus B. von KleinSmid (former University of Arizona Presidents). November 16, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Inaugural luncheon. November 16, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Inauguration ceremonies, including printed program. November 16, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Inauguration ceremonies, including photographs. November 16, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Dedication of Student Union, including printed program. November 17, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence: President Richard Harvill - Personal. No Date (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Acceptances, regrets, greetings from Academic and Professional Societies, A-Z. No Date (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Acceptances, regrets, greetings from miscellaneous persons, firms, and state groups. No Date (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Acceptances, regrets, greetings from United States Universities and Colleges, A-T. No Date (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Acceptances, regrets, greetings from United States Universities and Colleges, U-Z. No Date (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
- Acceptances, regrets, greetings from Foreign Universities, A-Z. No Date (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
- Clippings. No Date (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Alphabetical card file of Universities and Colleges, Academic and Professional Societies; and Foreign Universities who did not reply. No Date (Box 4)
- Phonograph recordings (5) of Richard Anderson Harvill speaking at the National Association of Manufacturer's meeting held on The University of Arizona campus. April 28, 1952 (Box 5)
- Phonograph recordings (8) of the Inauguration Ceremony. Includes addresses by the following individuals: Robert L. Nugent, vice-president of The University of Arizona; Cleon T. Knapp, president of the Board of Regents; James R. Miller, president of Northwestern University; and Howard Pyle, governor of Arizona. November 17, 1951 (Box 5)